Guide to the Letcher railroad collection, 1887-1889
Department of Special Collections
Letcher railroad collection,
1887-1889
Special Collections M0317
Letcher, Howard T., d. 1974.
.25 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of Gerald M. Best, 1980.
Biographical Note
Dr. Howard T. Letcher worked for the Shasta Division of the Southern Pacific Railroad in 1940 and 1941; he was a noted railroad historian and in 1971 was asked by then California Governor Ronald Reagan to serve on the board of directors of the Transportation museum in Sacramento, California.
Scope and Content
The addenda to the Letcher Railroad Collection consists of business correspondence of the Southern Pacific Company between Dec. 1887 and May 1889. The majority of the letters are addressed to William McKenzie, Asst. Genl. Master Mechanic, Sacramento, and H.J. Small, Supt. M.P.&M., Sacramento. The letters include daily reports of the operations of the railroad, employee problems, maintenance, and purchases. Of special interest are the three letters by G.J. Perkins, Engineer, about the engine El Governador No. 237, a large engine that Andrew Jackson Stevens, Supt. of Motive Power, was concerned with. A.J. Stevens was born in Vermont Sep. 14, 1833. In 1869 he was hired by Leland Stanford, President of Central Pacific (parent organization of Southern Pacific) as Master Mechanic. He was responsible for many locamotive inventions until his death in 1888. More information about the man and the El Gobernador is available in the Railway and Locomotive Historical Society Bulletin 65, pp 7 - 26.
Other company correspondents include:
Folders 13 through 18 have more complete listings of the correspondents inside each folder.
M 317 Letcher Railroad Collection Addenda
Container List
- [J. A. Gillmar?] to W. McKenzie, Dec. 24, 1887 - Feb. 15, 1888; 10 TLS (10) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Employee Problems; Engines; Repairs.
- [J. A. Gillmar?] to H. J. Small, Aug. 14, 1888 - March 14, 1889; 24 TLS (38); 1 ALS (1) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Repairs; Train Delays; Jobs.
- G. Gregg to W. McKenzie, Feb. 1, 1888 - April 21, 1888; 6 ALS (7) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Employee Problems; Engines; Fuel.
- G. Gregg to W. McKenzie, Oct. 8, 1888 - March 6, 1889; 13 ALS (19) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Engines; Car, Bad Order; Employee Problems.
- G. W. Carrole to W. McKenzie, Feb. 1889 - March 11, 1889; 5 ALS (7) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Employee Problems; Passes; Engines.
- [W. G. Crintis?] to W. McKenzie, Oct. 22, 1888 - March 13, 1889; 26 TLS (29) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Water; Brakes; Supplies; A. N. Towne; Fuel; Rates Pay.
- R. M. Pratt to W. McKenzie, H. J. Small, Feb. 8, 1888 - March 1, 1889; 4 TLS (4); 3 ALS (3) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Engines; Accidents.
- A. N. Towne to W. McKenzie, H. J. Small, Jan. 6, 1888 - Feb. 5, 1889; 8 TLS (9) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Passes; Scales; Jobs; Fuel.
- C. C. Bronte to H. J. Small, Nov. 7, 1888 - March 11, 1889; 3 TLS (3); 5 ALS (7) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Supplies; Coal; Rates Pay; Jobs; J. W. Pedler.
- M. W. Cooley to H. J. Small, Feb. 27, 1889 - March 14, 1889; 8 ALS (9) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Passes; Employee Problems; Repairs.
- M. J. Crosby to H. J. Small, Feb. 22, 1889 - March 1, 1889; 3 ALS (5) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Engines; Rates Pay.
- H. Stillman to H. J. Small, Nov. 5, 1888 to March 1, 1889; 5 ALS (7) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  J. Thorne; Supplies.
- Letters to W. McKenzie, Jan. 4, 1888 - April 8, 1888; 9 ALS (12) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Jobs; Employee Problems.
- Letters to H. J. Small, Feb. 26, 1888 - May 10, 1889; 7 TLS (7); 47 ALS (62) approximately (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Employee Problems; Supplies; Jobs; Train Delays; Supplies; Engines.
- Letters from G. J. Perkins, Dec. 6, 1887 - April 21, 1888; 3 ALS (6) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Engines; Repairs.
  Letter to A. J. Stevens
- Letters from [J. Barmer?], [G. C. Falent?], [N. M. Foster?], J. Harrington, J. W. Heintzelman, N. B. Kellogg, W. McKenzie, F. A. Steoins, Jan. 16, 1888 - March 15, 1889; 5 TLS (5); 14 ALS (20) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Engines; Mr. Stevens dies; Accidents; Rates Pay; Passes; Repairs; Supplies; Employee Problems (Mr. Yale).
- Letters, Notes, Misc., Feb. 1, 1888 - Feb. 27, 1889; Feb. 20, 1957; 4 TLS (5); 8 ALS (12) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Employee Problems; Jobs; Supplies.
  Letter to A. J. Stevens.
- Incomplete Letters, 3 ALS (5) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Repairs; Employee Problems (Mr. Yale).